Guide to the Clara Barrus Papers, 1901-1931
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Clara Barrus Papers
1901-1931
Barrus, Clara, 1864-1931
5.8 cubic feet (29 boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
The collection consists of correspondence from John Burroughs to Clara Barrus, and Barrus's journals, written from 1901 to 1924, which span the years in which she was acquainted with Burroughs. Also included are photographs, scraps of notes, and published articles written about or by Barrus.
Biographical Note
Clara Barrus was born in Port Byron, New York in 1864. She studied medicine at Boston University and received her Doctor of Medicine degree in 1888. For several years she was in private practice in Utica, New York, but in 1893 she became an assistant physician at the Middletown Hospital for the Insane. In addition, she served as professor of psychiatry at Women's College of New York City. She left Middletown Hospital after seventeen years, and in 1912 she opened a private sanitarium in Pelham, New York, until her retirement in 1914.
Doctor Barrus met John Burroughs while she was practicing medicine, and was associated with him for almost two decades, until his death in 1921. She was Burroughs' friend, secretary, biographer, and almost constant traveling companion. When he died, Barrus was named his literary executor. Among other works, she edited two posthumous volumes of Burroughs' essays, and wrote Whitman and Burroughs, Comrades (1931), about the relationship between Burroughs and poet Walt Whitman.
Clara Barrus died on April 4, 1931, after a long illness.
Scope and Content Note
The bulk of the Clara Barrus Papers is made up of correspondence from John Burroughs to Clara Barrus. Letters from Barrus to Burroughs can be found in the John Burroughs Papers. The rest of the collection is mostly superficial, containing photographs, scraps of notes, or published articles written about or by Barrus. The notable exception is a series of Clara Barrus' journals, written from 1901 to 1924, spanning the years in which she was acquainted with Burroughs.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library without any additional restrictions.
Related Materials
John Burroughs Collection
Subject Headings
Names:
Burroughs, John, 1837-1921
Document Types:
Correspondence; Clippings (information artifacts); Diaries; Photographs
VCL Categories:
Literature and Writing; Nature and Natural History
Encoding Information
Encoded by Laura Streett and Elizabeth Clarke, November 2006. Updated by Emma Gronbeck, October 2025.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Elizabeth Burroughs Kelley, granddaughter of John Burroughs, 1990.
Four letters from Clara Barrus to Charles E. Benton, and one photograph of Barrus with John Burroughs from 1917, were the gift of Susan Herley, 2025. [M2025-014]
Series List
- Series I. Correspondence, 1901-1931
- Series II. Notes and Notebooks, circa 1902-1924
- Series III. Material about John Burroughs, circa 1891-1902
- Series IV. Clippings and Photographs, 1903-1931
Container List
- SERIES I. CORRESPONDENCE, 1901-1931
  - Correspondence to Clara Barrus
    - Aiken, Helen, 1910; (1 letter) (Folder 1.1)
    - B., F.F., 1912 Aug; (1 postcard) (Folder 1.2)
    - Baker, Smith, [no year] Sep; (1 letter) (Folder 1.3)
    - Burr, Helen, 1919 Sep; (1 letter) (Folder 1.4)
    - Burroughs, John, 1901 May-Oct; (9 letters, 1 empty envelope) (Folder 1.5)
    - Burroughs, John, 1901 Nov; (5 letters) (Folder 1.6)
    - Burroughs, John, 1901 Dec 5-15; (5 letters) (Folder 1.7)
    - Burroughs, John, 1901 Dec 17-22; (3 letters) (Folder 1.8)
    - Burroughs, John, 1901 Dec 24-25; (3 letters) (Folder 1.9)
    - Burroughs, John, 1902 Jan 2-22; (9 letters) (Folder 1.10)
    - Burroughs, John, 1902 Jan 25-30; (5 letters) (Folder 1.11)
    - Burroughs, John, 1902 Feb; (4 letters) (Folder 2.1)
    - Burroughs, John, 1902 Mar-Apr; (7 letters, 1 telegram) (Folder 2.2)
    - Burroughs, John, 1902 Apr 3-15; (4 letters with 1 sprig of arbutus) (Folder 2.3)
    - Burroughs, John, 1902 Apr 17-27; (5 letters) (Folder 2.4)
    - Burroughs, John, 1902 May 2-12; (5 letters) (Folder 2.5)
    - Burroughs, John, 1902 May 14-31; (4 letters) (Folder 2.6)
    - Burroughs, John, 1902 Jun 7-16; (4 letters) (Folder 2.7)
    - Burroughs, John, 1902 Jun 17-24; (3 letters) (Folder 2.8)
    - Burroughs, John, 1902 Jul 4-13; (4 letters) (Folder 3.1)
    - Burroughs, John, 1902 Jul 18-29; (4 letters) (Folder 3.2)
    - Burroughs, John, 1902 Aug; (6 letters) (Folder 3.3)
    - Burroughs, John, 1902 Sep; (7 letters, 1 empty envelope) (Folder 3.4)
    - Burroughs, John, 1902 Oct 1-12; (4 letters) (Folder 3.5)
    - Burroughs, John, 1902 Oct 15-31; (5 letters) (Folder 3.6)
    - Burroughs, John, 1902 Nov 2-13; (4 letters) (Folder 3.7)
    - Burroughs, John, 1902 Nov 14-27; (3 letters, 1 empty envelope) (Folder 3.8)
    - Burroughs, John, 1902 Dec 2-12; (6 letters) (Folder 4.1)
    - Burroughs, John, 1902 Dec 18-31; (6 letters) (Folder 4.2)
    - Burroughs, John, 1903 Jan 2-9; (5 letters) (Folder 4.3)
    - Burroughs, John, 1903 Jan [10-14?]; (3 letters) (Folder 4.4)
    - Burroughs, John, 1903 Jan 19-29; (5 letters) (Folder 4.5)
    - Burroughs, John, 1903 Feb 5-14; (4 letters) (Folder 4.6)
    - Burroughs, John, 1903 Feb 16-23; (4 letters) (Folder 4.7)
    - Burroughs, John, 1903 Mar 2-12; (5 letters) (Folder 5.1)
    - Burroughs, John, 1903 Mar 15-21; (3 letters) (Folder 5.2)
    - Burroughs, John, 1903 Apr 1-5; (4 letters) (Folder 5.3)
    - Burroughs, John, 1903 Apr 10-28; (4 letters) (Folder 5.4)
    - Burroughs, John, 1903 May; (5 letters) (Folder 5.5)
    - Burroughs, John, 1903 Jun 3-19; (4 letters, 1 empty envelope) (Folder 5.6)
    - Burroughs, John, 1903 Jun 22-30; (4 letters) (Folder 5.7)
    - Burroughs, John, 1903 Jul 1-12; (3 letters) (Folder 5.8)
    - Burroughs, John, 1903 Jul 15-30; (4 letters) (Folder 5.9)
    - Burroughs, John, 1903 Aug; (5 letters) (Folder 6.1)
    - Burroughs, John, 1903 Sep; (4 letters) (Folder 6.2)
    - Burroughs, John, 1903 Oct; (8 letters) (Folder 6.3)
    - Burroughs, John, 1903 Nov; (8 letters) (Folder 6.4)
    - Burroughs, John, 1903 Dec 3-13; (4 letters) (Folder 6.5)
    - Burroughs, John, 1903 Dec 15-29; (5 letters) (Folder 6.6)
    - Burroughs, John, 1904 Jan; (8 letters) (Folder 6.7)
    - Burroughs, John, 1904 Feb; (7 letters) (Folder 6.8)
    - Burroughs, John, 1904 Mar; (8 letters) (Folder 7.1)
    - Burroughs, John, 1904 Apr 1-11; (5 letters) (Folder 7.2)
    - Burroughs, John, 1904 Apr 14-27; (5 letters) (Folder 7.3)
    - Burroughs, John, 1904 May; (6 letters, 1 empty envelope) (Folder 7.4)
    - Burroughs, John, 1904 Jun; (5 letters, 2 empty envelopes) (Folder 7.5)
    - Burroughs, John, 1904 Jul; (6 letters) (Folder 7.6)
    - Burroughs, John, 1904 Aug 1-15; (6 letters) (Folder 7.7)
    - Burroughs, John, 1904 Aug 20-31; (4 letters) (Folder 7.8)
    - Burroughs, John, 1904 Sep; (5 letters) (Folder 8.1)
    - Burroughs, John, 1904 Oct 5-17; (3 letters) (Folder 8.2)
    - Burroughs, John, 1904 Oct 20-28; (2 letters, 1 postcard) (Folder 8.3)
    - Burroughs, John, 1904 Nov; (4 letters) (Folder 8.4)
    - Burroughs, John, 1904 Dec; (7 letters) (Folder 8.5)
    - Burroughs, John, 1905 Jan-Feb; (9 letters) (Folder 9.1)
    - Burroughs, John, 1905 Mar; (8 letters) (Folder 9.2)
    - Burroughs, John, 1905 Apr; (5 letters, 1 empty envelope) (Folder 9.3)
    - Burroughs, John, 1905 May; (8 letters) (Folder 9.4)
    - Burroughs, John, 1905 Jun-Jul; (9 letters, 1 empty envelope) (Folder 9.5)
    - Burroughs, John, 1905 Aug-Sep; (12 letters, 1 postcard) (Folder 9.6)
    - Burroughs, John, 1905 Oct; (6 letters, 1 empty envelope) (Folder 9.7)
    - Burroughs, John, 1905 Nov; (6 letters, 1 empty envelope) (Folder 9.8)
    - Burroughs, John, 1905 Dec; (10 letters, 1 fragment) (Folder 9.9)
    - Burroughs, John, 1906 Jan; (7 letters, 2 empty envelopes) (Folder 10.1)
    - Burroughs, John, 1906 Feb; (6 letters) (Folder 10.2)
    - Burroughs, John, 1906 Mar; (7 letters) (Folder 10.3)
    - Burroughs, John, 1906 Apr; (4 letters) (Folder 10.4)
    - Burroughs, John, 1906 May; (10 letters) (Folder 10.5)
    - Burroughs, John, 1906 Jun; (11 letters) (Folder 10.6)
    - Burroughs, John, 1906 Aug; (11 letters) (Folder 10.7)
    - Burroughs, John, 1906 Sep; (7 letters, 1 postcard, 2 empty envelopes) (Folder 11.1)
    - Burroughs, John, 1906 Oct; (2 letters) (Folder 11.2)
    - Burroughs, John, 1906 Nov; (6 letters) (Folder 11.3)
    - Burroughs, John, 1906 Dec; (6 letters) (Folder 11.4)
    - Burroughs, John, 1907 Jan-Feb; (12 letters, 1 telegram) (Folder 11.5)
    - Burroughs, John, 1907 Mar; (8 letters, 1 empty envelope) (Folder 11.6)
    - Burroughs, John, 1907 Apr; (6 letters) (Folder 11.7)
    - Burroughs, John, 1907 May; (7 letters) (Folder 12.1)
    - Burroughs, John, 1907 Jun; (7 letters) (Folder 12.2)
    - Burroughs, John, 1907 Jul; (8 letters) (Folder 12.3)
    - Burroughs, John, 1907 Aug; (8 letters, 2 postcards) (Folder 12.4)
    - Burroughs, John, 1907 Sep; (5 letters, 1 empty envelope) (Folder 12.5)
    - Burroughs, John, 1907 Oct; (7 letters, 1 empty envelope) (Folder 12.6)
    - Burroughs, John, 1907 Nov; (7 letters) (Folder 12.7)
    - Burroughs, John, 1907 Dec; (8 letters) (Folder 12.8)
    - Burroughs, John, 1908 Jan; (10 letters, 1 empty envelope) (Folder 13.1)
    - Burroughs, John, 1908 Feb; (8 letters, 1 postcard, 1 empty envelope) (Folder 13.2)
    - Burroughs, John, 1908 Mar; (7 letters, 1 postcard) (Folder 13.3)
    - Burroughs, John, 1908 Apr-May; (11 letters, 1 empty envelope) (Folder 13.4)
    - Burroughs, John, 1908 Jun; (9 letters, 1 fragment, 2 empty envelopes) (Folder 13.5)
    - Burroughs, John, 1908 Jul; (5 letters) (Folder 13.6)
    - Burroughs, John, 1908 Aug; (6 letters, 2 empty envelopes) (Folder 13.7)
    - Burroughs, John, 1908 Sep; (4 letters, 2 postcards, 3 empty envelopes) (Folder 14.1)
    - Burroughs, John, 1908 Oct; (9 letters, 2 empty envelopes) (Folder 14.2)
    - Burroughs, John, 1908 Nov; (9 letters) (Folder 14.3)
    - Burroughs, John, 1908 Dec; (9 letters) (Folder 14.4)
    - Burroughs, John, 1909 Jan; (6 letters, 2 fragments, 1 postcard) (Folder 14.5)
    - Burroughs, John, 1909 Feb; (7 letters) (Folder 14.6)
    - Burroughs, John, 1909 Jun-Jul; (9 letters) (Folder 14.7)
    - Burroughs, John, 1909 Aug; (9 letters) (Folder 14.8)
    - Burroughs, John, 1909 Sep-Oct; (6 letters) (Folder 15.1)
    - Burroughs, John, 1909 Nov; (9 letters) (Folder 15.2)
    - Burroughs, John, 1909 Dec; (9 letters, 4 postcards) (Folder 15.3)
    - Burroughs, John, 1910 Jan; (7 letters, 2 postcards) (Folder 15.4)
    - Burroughs, John, 1910 Feb; (8 letters) (Folder 15.5)
    - Burroughs, John, 1910 Mar; (9 letters) (Folder 15.6)
    - Burroughs, John, 1910 Apr 4-9; (4 letters, 1 fragment) (Folder 15.7)
    - Burroughs, John, 1910 Apr 11-26; (6 letters, 1 telegram, 1 postcard) (Folder 15.8)
    - Burroughs, John, 1910 May 3-13; (4 letters, 3 postcards) (Folder 15.9)
    - Burroughs, John, 1910 May 21-23; (3 letters) (Folder 15.10)
    - Burroughs, John, 1910 Jun 1-18; (5 letters, 1 postcard) (Folder 15.11)
    - Burroughs, John, 1910 Jun 19-30; (5 letters) (Folder 16.1)
    - Burroughs, John, 1910 Jul 4-15; (6 letters, 1 postcard) (Folder 16.2)
    - Burroughs, John, 1910 Jul 13-31; (5 letters) (Folder 16.3)
    - Burroughs, John, 1910 Aug; (5 letters, 3 postcards) (Folder 16.4)
    - Burroughs, John, 1910 Sep; (8 letters, 2 postcards, 1 empty envelope) (Folder 16.5)
    - Burroughs, John, 1910 Oct; (7 letters) (Folder 16.6)
    - Burroughs, John, 1910 Nov; (7 letters, 2 postcards) (Folder 16.7)
    - Burroughs, John, 1910 Dec 1-15; (5 letters) (Folder 16.8)
    - Burroughs, John, 1910 Dec 17-29; (5 letters, 1 telegram) (Folder 16.9)
    - Burroughs, John, 1911 Jan; (2 letters) (Folder 17.1)
    - Burroughs, John, 1911 Apr; (5 letters, 1 postcard) (Folder 17.2)
    - Burroughs, John, 1911 May; (8 letters, 2 postcards) (Folder 17.3)
    - Burroughs, John, 1911 Jun 1-11; (4 letters, 2 postcards) (Folder 17.4)
    - Burroughs, John, 1911 Jun 14-22; (5 letters, 2 postcards) (Folder 17.5)
    - Burroughs, John, 1911 Oct 11-17; (5 letters, 1 postcard) (Folder 17.6)
    - Burroughs, John, 1911 Oct 20-28; (5 letters, 1 postcard) (Folder 17.7)
    - Burroughs, John, 1911 Nov; (7 letters) (Folder 17.8)
    - Burroughs, John, 1911 Dec; (5 letters) (Folder 17.9)
    - Burroughs, John, 1912 Jan 1-8; (3 letters) (Folder 17.10)
    - Burroughs, John, 1912 Jan 21-29; (3 letters, 3 postcards, 1 telegram) (Folder 17.11)
    - Burroughs, John, 1912 Feb; (2 letters, 7 postcards) (Folder 17.12)
    - Burroughs, John, 1912 Mar; (8 letters, 1 postcard, 1 telegram) (Folder 18.1)
    - Burroughs, John, 1912 Apr; (7 letters) (Folder 18.2)
    - Burroughs, John, 1912 May 1-7; (5 letters, 2 postcards) (Folder 18.3)
    - Burroughs, John, 1912 May 8-29; (7 letters, 2 postcards) (Folder 18.4)
    - Burroughs, John, 1912 Jun; (9 letters, 2 postcards) (Folder 18.5)
    - Burroughs, John, 1912 Jul; (4 letters) (Folder 18.6)
    - Burroughs, John, 1912 Aug-Sep; (9 letters, 1 postcard) (Folder 18.7)
    - Burroughs, John, 1912 Oct; (7 letters, 1 postcard) (Folder 18.8)
    - Burroughs, John, 1912 Nov; (5 letters, 1 postcard) (Folder 18.9)
    - Burroughs, John, 1912 Dec; (6 letters) (Folder 18.10)
    - Burroughs, John, 1913 Jan; (3 letters, 3 postcards) (Folder 19.1)
    - Burroughs, John, 1913 Feb; (3 letters, 1 postcard) (Folder 19.2)
    - Burroughs, John, 1913 Mar 1-16; (8 letters, 1 postcard) (Folder 19.3)
    - Burroughs, John, 1913 Mar 17-31; (4 letters, 1 telegram, 5 postcards) (Folder 19.4)
    - Burroughs, John, 1913 Apr; (6 letters) (Folder 19.5)
    - Burroughs, John, 1913 May; (4 letters, 1 postcard) (Folder 19.6)
    - Burroughs, John, 1913 Jun; (6 letters, 3 postcards) (Folder 19.7)
    - Burroughs, John, 1913 Jul; (1 letter, 2 postcards) (Folder 19.8)
    - Burroughs, John, 1913 Sep-Nov; (3 letters, 5 postcards) (Folder 19.9)
    - Burroughs, John, 1913 Dec; (6 letters, 2 postcards) (Folder 19.10)
    - Burroughs, John, 1914 Jan; (6 letters, 1 postcard) (Folder 19.11)
    - Burroughs, John, 1914 Feb; (4 letters, 1 postcard) (Folder 20.1)
    - Burroughs, John, 1914 Mar; (6 letters) (Folder 20.2)
    - Burroughs, John, 1914 Apr; (8 letters) (Folder 20.3)
    - Burroughs, John, 1914 May; (7 letters, 1 postcard) (Folder 20.4)
    - Burroughs, John, 1914 Jun-Dec; (4 letters) (Folder 20.5)
    - Burroughs, John, 1915 Feb; (6 letters, 1 postcard) (Folder 20.6)
    - Burroughs, John, 1915 Mar; (7 letters, 1 postcard) (Folder 20.7)
    - Burroughs, John, 1915 May-Dec; (6 letters, 2 postcards) (Folder 20.8)
    - Burroughs, John, 1916 Jan 1-14; (5 letters, 2 postcards) (Folder 20.9)
    - Burroughs, John, 1916 Jan 17-31; (7 letters, 1 postcard) (Folder 20.10)
    - Burroughs, John, 1916 Feb; (2 letters, 1 postcard, 1 telegram) (Folder 21.1)
    - Burroughs, John, 1916 Mar; (6 letters, 1 postcard) (Folder 21.2)
    - Burroughs, John, 1916 May-Jul; (3 letters, 5 postcards) (Folder 21.3)
    - Burroughs, John, 1916 Aug 1-10; (3 letters) (Folder 21.4)
    - Burroughs, John, 1916 Aug 16-20; (3 letters) (Folder 21.5)
    - Burroughs, John, 1916 Sep-Nov; (6 letters, 5 postcards) (Folder 21.6)
    - Burroughs, John, 1916 Nov 16-29; (7 letters, 1 telegram, 2 postcards) (Folder 21.7)
    - Burroughs, John, 1916 Dec; (4 letters) (Folder 21.8)
    - Burroughs, John, 1917 Feb; (3 letters, 1 postcard) (Folder 21.9)
    - Burroughs, John, 1917 Mar; (5 letters, 1 postcard) (Folder 22.1)
    - Burroughs, John, 1917 Apr-Jun; (4 letters) (Folder 22.2)
    - Burroughs, John, 1917 Oct-Dec; (6 letters, 1 postcard) (Folder 22.3)
    - Burroughs, John, 1918 Jan-May; (2 letters, 3 postcards) (Folder 22.4)
    - Burroughs, John, 1918 Jul-Dec; (5 letters) (Folder 22.5)
    - Burroughs, John, 1919 Jan-Aug; (4 letters, 6 postcards) (Folder 22.6)
    - Burroughs, John, 1919 Oct; (7 letters, 3 postcards) (Folder 22.7)
    - Burroughs, John, 1919 Nov-Dec; (5 letters, 4 postcards) (Folder 22.8)
    - Burroughs, John, 1920; (1 letter) (Folder 22.9)
    - C., H.C., 1910 Sep; (1 letter) (Folder 23.1)
    - [Cordoba, M.?], undated; (1 fragment) (Folder 23.2)
    - DeLoach, R.J.H., 1912, 1916; (3 letters) (Folder 23.2a)
    - Drake, A.W.(Century Company), 1910 Mar; (1 letter) (Folder 23.3)
    - Ford, Mrs. Henry, 1923 Aug; (1 fragment) (Folder 23.4)
    - Forsyth, Sara, 1921 Sep; (1 letter, 1 annotated) (Folder 23.5)
    - Gilbert, E.S., 1921, undated; (2 letters, 1 annotated) (Folder 23.6)
    - Hendrick, Elizabeth, 1916 Aug; (1 letter) (Folder 23.7)
    - Howell, George, 1916 Aug; (1 letter) (Folder 23.8)
    - Johns, Aaron and Annie, 1921-1925; (9 letters) (Folder 23.9)
    - Moore, Fillmore, [no year] Apr; (1 letter) (Folder 23.10)
    - Perry, Burroughs F., 1921 Apr; (1 letter) (Folder 23.11)
    - Philputt, J.M., 1910 Feb; (1 letter) (Folder 23.12)
    - Plummer, Charles, 1921 Mar; (1 letter, 1 annotated) (Folder 23.13)
    - Sherk, Henry H., 1921-1924; (3 letters) (Folder 23.14)
    - Vanamee, Grace, 1916 Aug; (1 letter, 1 enclosure) (Folder 23.15)
    - Warren, Grace T., [no year] Jul; (1 letter) (Folder 23.16)
    - Winslow, Anne G., [no year] Jul; (1 letter) (Folder 23.17)
    - Woodworth, Nelly, 1916 Aug; (1 letter) (Folder 23.18)
    - empty envelopes (2), 1912-1924 (Folder 23.19)
    - M.C. Drake to Addie Barrus Johnson, 1910 Sep; (1 letter) (Folder 23.20)
  - Correspondence from Clara Barrus
    - Benton, Charles E., 1913-1923; (2 letters, 2 postcards) (Folder 28.10)
    - [Burroughs], Julian, [no year] Jun; (1 postcard) (Folder 23.21)
    - Burroughs, Ursula, 1909; (6 letters, 1 annotated) (Folder 23.22)
    - Burroughs, Ursula, 1910; (5 letters) (Folder 23.23)
    - Burroughs, Ursula, 1911; (3 letters) (Folder 23.24)
    - Drake, Ruth, 1921 Apr; (1 letter and transcript) (Folder 23.25)
    - Haring, H.A., 1921-1931; (13 letters, 1 annotated) (Folder 23.26)
    - Reed [Vassar student], 1919; (1 letter [transcript]) (Folder 24.1)
    - Worthington, Ruth, 1926 Sep; (1 letter) (Folder 24.2)
    - Barrus "letter" in French, undated; (1 letter) (Folder 24.3)
- SERIES II. NOTES AND NOTEBOOKS, circa 1902-1924
  - Notes on corrections of MSS, circa 1902, undated; (MS, 3 p., photocopies, 2 annotated) (Folder 24.3)
  - Our Santa Claus, 1920; (MS, 2 p.) (Folder 24.4)
  - copies of inscriptions CB wrote in books for friends, undated; (MS, 6 p.) (Folder 24.5)
  - miscellaneous notes, undated; (MS/TS, 3 p., 3 fragments) (Folder 24.6)
  - A Study in Handwriting by Elizabeth Tuttle, 1901 Oct; (MS, 2 p.) (Folder 24.7)
  - Notes by EBK on a brochure printed by CB, undated; (MS, 2 p.) (Folder 24.8)
  - Journal, 1901-1904; (MS, 94 p., 2 p. annotated) (Folder 24.9)
  - Journal, photocopy, 1901-1904; (MS, 119 p.) (Folder 24.10)
  - Journal, 1905 Jan, 1918 Jul; (MS, 6 p.) (Folder 25.1)
  - Journal, 1911 May-Oct, 1913 Jul, 1914 Jul-Sep; (MS, 73 p.) (Folder 25.2)
  - Journal Kelley transcript, 1914 Jun-Jul; (MS, 2 p.) (Folder 25.3)
  - Journal, 1915; (TS, 7 p., 1 annotated) (Folder 25.4)
  - Journal, 1916; (TS, 9 p., 1 annotated) (Folder 25.5)
  - Journal, 1916-1917; (TS, 25 p., photocopy) (Folder 25.6)
  - Journal, 1917; (MS, 120 p.) (Folder 25.7)
  - Journal, 1918 Jan-Apr; (MS, 100 p.) (Folder 25.8)
  - Journal, 1918 Apr-Dec; (MS, 167 p.) (Folder 26.1)
  - Journal, 1919 Jan-Dec; (MS, 203 p.) (Folder 26.2)
  - Journal, 1919 Dec; (MS, 24 p., 1 annotated) (Folder 26.3)
  - Journal, 1920 Jan-Mar; (MS, 75 p.) (Folder 26.4)
  - Journal, 1920 Apr 1-16; (MS, 7 p., photocopy, 1 annotated) (Folder 26.5)
  - Journal, 1920 Apr-Jul; (MS, 99 p.) (Folder 27.1)
  - Journal, 1920 Jul-Dec; (MS, 108 p.) (Folder 27.2)
  - Journal, 1921 Jan-Mar; (MS, 49 p.) (Folder 27.3)
  - Journal [Kelley transcript?], 1921 Mar 25-27; (MS, 7 p.) (Folder 27.4)
  - Journal, 1924 Jan-Apr; (MS, 49 p., 1 annotated) (Folder 27.5)
  - Scrapbook, circa 1903-1913 (Box 29)
- SERIES III. MATERIAL ABOUT JOHN BURROUGHS, circa 1891-1902
  - Reminiscences of Burroughs by Barrus, circa 1891-1902; (MS, 13 p.) (Folder 28.1)
  - Notes by Barrus on Burroughs' book on Audubon, undated; (MS, 2 p., 1 annotated) (Folder 28.2)
  - Notes by Barrus to Burroughs (criticisms of MSS), undated; (MS/TS, 14 p., 3 annotated) (Folder 28.3)
  - List of articles about Burroughs, undated; (MS, 1 p., 1 annotated) (Folder 28.4)
- SERIES IV. CLIPPINGS AND PHOTOGRAPHS, 1903-1931
  - Articles by Barrus, 1903-1928, undated; (37 p., 1 annotated) (Folder 28.5)
  - Articles about Barrus, 1914-1928, undated; (10 p., 1 annotated) (Folder 28.6)
  - Obituaries of Barrus, 1931; (2 p., photocopies) (Folder 28.7)
  - Miscellaneous clippings, 1910-1911, undated; (17 p., 2 annotated) (Folder 28.8)
  - Photographs, undated; (7 photographs, 1 annotated) (Folder 28.9)
  - Photograph - Barrus with John Burroughs, 1917 May 27; (1 annotated photograph) (Folder 28.11)